All
right, good morning. My name is Dan Margulies, I'm filling for Rabbi
Linzer while he's away. Today is the 20th of אב, Av, it's
the 24th of August and we will be picking up toward the
bottom of page 84 on עמוד ב', amud bet, right
where the גמרא Gemara says צער. tza’ar. So the משנה Mishnah had
said צער. tza’ar. In what circumstances do you pay, or not what
circumstances, but how do we evaluate the payment for pain and suffering?
So the משנה Mishnah had suggested an analysis that said צער כוואו
בשיפוד או במסמר ואפילו על צפורנו מקום שאינו עושה חבורה אומדים כמה
אדם כיוצא בזה רוצה ליטול להיות מצטער כך.
tza’ar kavo bishipud o bamasmer ve’afillu al tziporno makom she’eino oseh chavurah
omdim kamah adam kayotze bezeh
rotzeh litol lihyot mista’er kach.
What would you do to assess pain and suffering? Suppose a person
either stabbed someone or burned someone with something very thin and sharp,
some sort of a spear, some sort of a nail, and even
on the fingernail, which is a place which does not leave a
חבורה—I chavurah don't know, I've had bruises under my fingernail before—maybe it
doesn't mean bruise, maybe it means the wound. That is, if someone
would poke you on your fingernail, you can assess how much pain
it would be even if it doesn't leave any permanent mark. That
is, the fingernail is more resistant. Or maybe it means underneath the
fingernail is a very sensitive spot.
Hard to tell. Okay, but מקום שאינו עושה חבורה. makom she’eino oseh
chavurah. That's going to become important. A place that does not leave
a wound or does not leave a bruise, we evaluate how much
a person like this, that is of a similar person, would be
willing to pay, or would really would be willing to be paid,
in order to undergo such suffering. That is, if you tell me,
I'll say, how much should I give you to let me poke
you with this needle? Or how much should you—would you let me
pay you in order to chop off your finger or something like
that? So we're going to have to see how the גמרא Gemara
goes into that. But the first discussion is going to be about
this question of leaving a wound or leaving a bruise behind. So
the גמרא Gemara says: צער כוואו בשיפוד ובמסמר. tza’ar kavo bishipud u’bamasmer.
Is cutting the finger just a further extension?
So we're going to have to see. The cutting, amputation of a
limb is going to obviously have much more extensive other parts of
the damages to be assessed as well. So the גמרא Gemara says:
צער שלא במקום נזק משתלם. tza’ar shelo bemakom nezek mishtalem.
You could even pay צער, tza’ar, that is for pain and suffering,
even if there's no נזק, nezek, even if there's no permanent damage.
What does that mean? That means if there's an injury which could
fully heal, so there's no devaluation or no appreciable long-term damage that
this person undergoes because of this injury, the only thing is pain
and suffering. So that's why the question of whether it leaves a
bruise or not becomes important. Because the bruise or the wound could
be something that lasts forever. But if it's even in a place
that does not leave a bruise, then you could understand that צער
tza’ar could be paid even when there's no נזק. nezek. We saw
previously some of the other five, some of the other four would
be משתלם במקום נזק. mishtalem bemakom nezek. Only in a case where
you would pay נזק nezek would you also pay these. We're going
to see as well, some of the others become equated, like שבת
shevet comes connected with ריפוי. rippuy. So here, צער tza’ar even שלא
במקום נזק משתלם. shelo bemakom nezek mishtalem. מאן תנא? Man tana? So
which תנא tanna is that? That is, which תנא tanna is our
משנה Mishnah like? That is that you would pay צער tza’ar even
if there's no נזק? nezek? אמר רבא בן עזאי היא. Amar Rava:
Ben Azzai hi. It must be בן עזאי'ס Ben Azzai's opinion. דתניא.
Detanya. We have a ברייתא Baraita which explicates this מחלוקת machlokes more
fully. בן עזאי היא דתניא רבי אומר כוייה נאמרה תחילה. Ben Azzai
hi detanya Rabbi omer: keviyah neemrah techilah. The פסוק pasuk referring to
different types of injuries included under עין תחת עין ayin tachat ayin
says כוייה keviyah first. כוייה, Keviyah, at least for now let's say
it means a burn. But it's not clear necessarily it means referring
to an injury which may or may not be presumed to leave
some kind of permanent injury. We're going to see that's the מחלוקת
machlokes between רבי Rabbi and בן עזאי. Ben Azzai. So רבי Rabbi
says כוייה נאמרה תחילה. keviyah neemrah techilah. בן עזאי אומר חבורה נאמרה
תחילה. Ben Azzai omer chavurah neemrah techilah. בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, either
analyzing another פסוק pasuk that lists them in a different order or
perhaps parsing the פסוק pasuk differently, suggests that חבורה, chavurah, a bruise
or a wound,
is what's mentioned first. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamifligi? How can they have
this kind of מחלוקת? machlokes? So רבי סבר כוייה דלית בה חבורה
משמע. Rabbi savar keviyah dela it beih chavurah mashma. So a כוייה,
keviyah, your instinct would be to assume that כוייה keviyah does not
leave a wound or does not leave a bruise for a long-term
injury. So כתב רחמנא חבורה לגלויי עליה דכוייה דאית בה חבורה אין
אי לא לא. ketav rachmana chavurah legaluyei aleih dekeviyah de'it beih chavurah
in, ilo lo. So therefore the תורה Torah was explicit and said
not only כוייה, keviyah, but also mentioned the word חבורה chavurah to
teach you that only if there is also a חבורה chavurah would
you pay for צער. tza’ar. That is, only if there is also
נזק nezek would you pay צער. tza’ar. That's רבי'ס Rabbi's position. ובן
עזאי סבר כוייה דאית בה חבורה משמע. U'Ben Azzai savar keviyah de'it
beih chavurah mashma. Our instinct would be to assume that a כוייה
keviyah does have a long-term injury, does create a חבורה. chavurah. So
כתב רחמנא חבורה לגלויי עליה דכוייה דלית בה חבורה. ketav rachmana chavurah
legaluyei aleih dekeviyah dela it beih chavurah.
And therefore so the תורה Torah was explicit to mention חבורה chabburah
to teach you that כויה kiva could refer even to an injury
that does not cause a long-term damage and therefore בן עזאי Ben
Azzai would say you would pay for צער שלא במקום נזק. tza'ar
she-lo b'makom nezek. So רבי Rebbe thinks כויה kiva you would naturally
assume refers to an injury which does not cause a long-term damage.
Therefore the תורה Torah was explicit to mention חבורה chabburah to include
those injuries which do not have long-term damage. בן עזאי Ben Azzai
thinks it's the opposite. כויה kiva you would think כויה kiva means
something that does have a long-term damage. Therefore the תורה Torah was
explicit to mention חבורה chabburah to say כויה kiva could even refer
to an injury which does not have long-term damage. Okay and therefore
they have a מחלוקת machlokes whether or not you would pay צער
tza'ar in a case where there was no נזק nezek where there
was no devaluation of the person's price on the slave market that
is no real long-term lasting physical injury. It's just about the pain
and suffering temporarily but it will heal.
You think this is a hermeneutic of כלל ופרט klal u-prat or
פרט וכלל? prat u-klal?
We're going to get there. Okay sorry. So מתקיף לה רב פפא.
matkif la Rav Papa. So רב פפא Rav Papa disagrees with רבא'ס
Rava's analysis. And רב פפא Rav Papa says like this: אדרבה איפכא
מסתברא. Adarabba ipcha mistabra. No the whole opposite makes more sense to
say like this. רבי אומר כויה נאמרה תחילה. Rebbe omer kiva ne'emrah
techillah. רבי Rebbe thinks that the פסוק pasuk mentions כויה kiva first.
סבר כויה דאית בה חבורה משמע Savar kiva d'it be chabburah mashma
sounds like כויה kiva is one that does create a wound does
create a bruise. So כתב רחמנא חבורה לגלויי אלא דכויה דלית בה
חבורה. katav rachmana chabburah l'galuyei ela d'kiva d'leit be chabburah. So then
the תורה Torah was explicit to mention חבורה chabburah to tell you
that it's including something that does not cause a wound. בן עזאי
אומר חבורה נאמרה תחילה. Ben Azzai omer chabburah ne'emrah techillah. So בן
עזאי Ben Azzai thinks the תורה Torah mentioned חבורה chabburah first. סבר
כויה דלית בה חבורה משמע. Savar kiva d'leit be chabburah mashma. He
thinks that כויה kiva means a wound an injury that does not
cause a lasting wound. משמע כתב רחמנא חבורה Mashma katav rachmana chabburah
therefore the תורה Torah mentioned חבורה chabburah to include לגלויי אלא דכויה
דאית בה חבורה l'galuyei ela d'kiva d'it be chabburah אי אלו לא
in ilu lo to distinguish between those injuries which do create a
lasting wound that you would pay צער tza'ar and נזק nezek and
to exclude those that do not leave a lasting injury that you
would be exempted even from צער. tza'ar. Okay so רב פפא Rav
Papa reads the ברייתא braisa exactly the opposite of רבא. Rava. Okay.
והכא במאי קמיפלגי Ve-hacha b'mai kamiphalgi אינמי דכולי עלמא כויה בין דאית
בה חבורה בין דלית בה חבורה משמע. inami de-kulei alma kiva bein
d'it be chabburah bein d'leit be chabburah mashma.
So it sounds like our conclusion should be that the word כויה
kiva does refer to an injury even if it does not create
a lasting injury. והכא בכלל ופרט המרוחקין זה מזה
קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha be-klal u-prat ham'ruchakin zeh mizeh kamiphalgi. No the מחלוקת machlokes
between רבי Rebbe and בן עזאי Ben Azzai is not actually about
what the word כויה kiva means or what the word חבורה chabburah
means and how the תורה Torah is talking about those kinds of
injuries. Rather it's they have a מחלוקת machlokes about how to apply
a דרשה d'rasha which is usually where most of our מחלוקות machlokos
come from and their disagreement is about how do we apply the
principle כלל ופרט klal u-prat if the כלל klal and the פרט
prat are far apart from each other. כלל ופרט Klal u-prat usually
says we have a general statement followed immediately by some of the
details. So we say that the כלל klal the generality is limited
to apply only to cases which are similar or comparable to the
פרט. prat. Question is what if the פרט prat is not right
next to it but what if it's a few words separated? So
that's the question. רבי סבר אין דנין אותו בכלל ופרט. Rebbe savar
ein danino oto b'klal u-prat. Right? It's four words apart and רש"י
Rashi discusses what are the words in between.
Like כויה תחת
כויה פצע תחת פצע
kva'at
tachat
kva'at p'tza tachat p'tza four words
there. There you go. פצע תחת חבורה.
P'tza
tachat chabburah.
So פצע פצע p'tza p'tza is in between כויה kiva and חבורה.
chabburah. So רבי סבר אין דנין אותו בכלל ופרט. Rebbe savar ein
danino oto b'klal u-prat. רבי Rebbe thinks therefore because of the words
describing the פצע p'tza פצע p'tza is another kind of injury
are in between the כויה kiva the burn and the חבורה chabburah
the bruise so therefore you could not apply כלל ופרט klal u-prat
and therefore חבורה chabburah does not come to limit what kind of
כויה kiva you would have and therefore רבי Rebbe would say even
if it does not cause a long-term injury you would still pay
צער tza'ar even if there's no נזק. nezek. Okay. בן עזאי סבר
דנין אותו בכלל ופרט Ben Azzai savar danino oto b'klal u-prat
and בן עזאי Ben Azzai thinks even if there's a few words
in between you would still apply כלל ופרט. klal u-prat. וכי תימא
חבורה דרבי למה לי? Ve-chi teima chabburah de-Rebbe lama li? So then
why does רבי Rebbe have to have the word חבורה chabburah at
all because he can't apply this כלל ופרט? klal u-prat? So he
says לדמי מיטמטרין. l'dmamei mitematrin. So what does לדמי מיטמטרין l'dmamei mitematrin
mean? It sounds like that there's a certain additional amount that you
would pay not just to pay the צער tza'ar but also to
pay נזק. nezek. That is if it causes a חבורה chabburah you
also have to pay for the נזק. nezek. It's not just the
צער. tza'ar. Our whole formulation up until now had been נזק nezek
is basically primary. Every kind of damage case you're paying נזק. nezek.
And then the question is with פרק החובל Perek ha-Chovel we were
introduced to the other four. That is and then on top of
the נזק nezek there are other things you have to pay for
if one person injures another. So here Here, רבי Rebbi kind of
flips it around a little bit, that is between human beings, the
fundamental thing that you're paying for seemingly is actually צער. Tza'ar. You're
paying for the pain that you cause with this injury. And then
the question is and if it leaves a permanent injury that will
never heal, if you cut off someone's finger, if you cut off
someone's nose, if they have a big scar, then the question is
going to be, okay, so now how do we assess the נזק.
Nezek. But in terms of human beings, rather than כלים Keilim let's
say, your house falls down, that's something where the depreciable damage is
what's most readily apparent. Between human beings, actually the צער Tza'ar is
the primary component, that's because it's sort of most locally centralized in
the person. We're going to see later on this דף, Daf, this
דף Daf actually has a lot of the medical, many different medical
themes, so certainly an interesting דף. Daf. So let's keep going. The
גמרא Gemara says אומדין כמה אדם כיוצא בזה רוצה ליטול. Omdin kama
adam k'yotzei baze rotzeh litol. That is, if you're on a game
show and they're going to say, okay, we're going to, you know,
hit you with a sledgehammer, we'll pay you $50,000, and
would you agree to that?
It's a game show that, you know, it's...
I don't know, I don't mean to rely on too many, too
many stereotypes but there's a, there's a sense of a stereotype that
certain Japanese game shows are very cruel, cruel kinds of punishments and
things like that, what's the, the Simpsons episode they say, your game
show rewards intelligence, our game show punishes ignorance, so something like that.
So anyway, okay, so אומדין כמה אדם רוצה ליטול. Omdin kama adam
rotzeh litol. Right,
or eating disgusting, eating a טרייף Treif bug. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says we have to assess how much a person like this
would be willing to be paid in order to undergo this kind
of thing. So צער במקום נזק היכי שמינן. Tza'ar bimkom nezek heichi
sham'inan. But then how can you assess צער Tza'ar in a case
where there was also נזק? Nezek? Why? Because
the payment that the person would be willing to accept is going
to cover both the צער Tza'ar and the נזק. Nezek. Because if
you're going to say how much would you be willing to let
us pay you to cut off your finger, but that includes the
permanent damage that's incurred, that is the person will no longer have
a finger, and the pain and suffering. So there's no way to
decouple the צער Tza'ar from the נזק. Nezek. That's the גמרא's Gemara
question. So אמר אבוה דשמואל, Amar avuha d'Shmuel, שמואל's Shmuel father: Wait,
sorry, but you do, I mean, because that's the value on the
slave market. That's ne...
Oh, but then we know how to evaluate the נזק. Nezek. נזק
Nezek you evaluate by saying slave market value. And then צער Tza'ar
you're supposed to say how much would this person want to be
paid in order to undergo this kind of pain? The problem is
if I say, okay, so you chopped off someone's finger, so now
we have to figure out how much money we should pay you
in בית דין Beis Din for that, then the question becomes, so
how do I evaluate the צער? Tza'ar? I say, how much would
you be willing to be paid in order to cut off your
finger? The problem is cutting off your finger is an act which
includes both נזק Nezek and צער Tza'ar and בושת Boshet and right,
each one of those components. But that's not the question.
The question is how much pain, just from a pain, and then...
But then there's no way for a human being to process just
the pain because a person immediately starts to think what is it
going to be that I have to live without my finger for
the rest of my life, that's going to include what's included in
the נזק Nezek as well.
So you're going to be double counting the נזק. Nezek. No, but
this is a very subjective, subjective scale to use if somebody's got
a lot of money, then they're not going to, they don't, what
are they going to say about this? I want to, you know,
I'll take this much money to have that done.
Right, you're saying... and this is why there's a concern about the
organ, black market organs, is that people who are less financially well
off might be more inclined to sell a kidney at a price
which is less than what it's really worth because they want quick
money fast and they're willing to sub... something like that. So that
may be a bias in this process that is incredibly subjective.
It's also an indispensable instrument.
How much are you willing to pay to undergo anesthetic and do
it versus how much you'd pay to...
We're going to get to that, we're going to get to that,
that's the גמרא's Gemara answer more or less. So let's see the
גמרא's Gemara answer. We said היכי שמינן. Heichi sham'inan. Okay.
Yeah, but the
difference between, you know, the effect of pain on somebody and trying
to objectify it in terms of a monetary...
Right, well that's incredibly true. That's exactly part of this question. So
we see, so אמר אבוה דשמואל. Amar avuha d'Shmuel. So שמואל's Shmuel
father, we see שמואל's Shmuel father a number of places in ש"ס,
Shas, sometimes שמואל... Shmuel... שמואל Shmuel was a doctor, wasn't he? שמואל,
Shmuel, I think there's some suggestion that שמואל, Shmuel, I mean again,
a doctor in the third, fourth century is not exactly the same
as a doctor nowadays. At that time, it was better than nothing,
that's true. Well maybe, it depends. Okay. אמר אבוה דשמואל: Amar avuha
d'Shmuel: אומדין כמה אדם רוצה ליטול. Omdin kama adam rotzeh litol. So
we see how much a person would be willing to take לקטוע
לו ידו, Liktoa lo yado, to cut off his hand, לקטוע לו
ידו, Liktoa lo yado, לא צער לחודאיהו. Lo Tza'ar lachudai-hu. So how
can you, that's exactly the point I was just saying, that is
אבוה דשמואל Avuha d'Shmuel suggests, oh we'll just see how much a
person is willing to have their hand cut off, but then you're
going to get into the problem of how do you decouple צער
Tza'ar from נזק. Nezek. How do you get צער לחודאיה? Tza'ar lachudai?
How do you get the צער Tza'ar by itself? So הכול הוא
חמישה דברים ניקה. Hakol hu chamisha devarim nika. It has all five
things. So עוד בשופטני עסקינן. Od beshofteini askinan. Okay, we're talking about
a case where sort of they're saying like you have to deal
with it. ועוד בשופטי עסקינן. ve'od beshoftei askinan. Okay, and we're talking
about a case where sort of they're saying like you have to
deal with it quickly, you have to deal with the case, אלא
לקטוע ידו. ela likto'a yado.
Wait, what does שופטי shoftei mean?
שופטי, shoftei, I think,
was like, no wait,
I always thought of it as something silly, like
who would want to do that? Yeah.
Oh just... Oh I found it. The point is that the person
is on... the person, any person who'd be willing to actually assess
a... no person is going to give you a realistic value for
that kind of assessment. Because a person would say, "What? Are you
crazy? I'm going to cut off my hand?" Like there's no such
evaluation. This is the סתם stam
respondent of אבוה דשמואל, avuh dishmuel, correct?
Correct. Right. They have two problems. Number one, you can't decouple צער
tza'ar from the other four. And number two, it sounds absurd. Like
no sane person would be willing to even have the conversation with
you about how much money would be involved.
You have a... this is very interesting. So the word I see
there is שופטי shoftei in there, right?
Which obviously is not what they're saying. Very interesting like, you know,
if there's like some sort of... I don't know the etymology of
the word. Okay, אלא לקטוע ידו הקטועה. ela likto'a yado haktu'ah. So
then we'll say so how much would you be willing to cut
off your hand that's already cut off? How's that? Okay, so it
means presumably it means that the person has some... or no, that
a person maybe has a degenerative illness and the question is, you
know, the person has a gangrenous hand or something like that. It's
already has an infection. It's going to have... it's going to fall
off on its own or someone has leprosy or something and the
injury is such that the limb will be lost no matter what.
The question is, okay, so now, like I could cut it off
now and it will be painful or it'll happen on its own
eventually.
Kind of the same thing.
It's not the same thing. So we'll see.
So okay, לקטוע ידו הקטועה, likto'a yado haktu'ah, ידו הקטועה נמי לא
צער לחודיה. yado haktu'ah nami lo tza'ar lechudei.
So why? איכא הא צער ובושת איכא. ika ha tza'ar uvoshet ika.
So it has both צער tza'ar and both בושת boshet too because
you're quickening the point in time at which this person no longer
has a hand. It's a certain amount of embarrassment involved in having
an amputation. Obviously part of that question is involved in discussing the
broader question about how
people with physical disabilities are treated in our society. If we are
assuming that there is some sort of embarrassment involved in having a
physical disability, obviously that means something also about how people should be
acting toward people who have these injuries and these disabilities as well.
Okay, דכסיפא ליה מילתא למשדא בבשרו לכלבי. dechasifa lei milta lemishda bevissaro
lachalvei.
It's very graphic. Why? Because what's going to happen? That limb will
be amputated and they're going to take it and take from your
flesh and just throw it to the dogs.
That's very interesting. Like, you know, what about... what about burying these
things? I hear that...
That's exactly the question. So in one of the תשובות teshuvot about
what to do in cases of amputation, I think it's from the
שבות יעקב, shevut yaakov, he discusses all the other גמרות gemarot that
talk about well if you have an amputated limb that's אבר מן
החי. eiver min hachai. So אבר מן החי eiver min hachai we
know is מטמא. metamei. That is, a כהן kohen certainly can't be
involved in handling or even being in the same room as an
amputated limb and things like that, which involves many complications for כהנים
kohanim who want to become surgeons or even doctors in general. But
that's a whole separate question. But the other question is אבר מן
החי eiver min hachai we usually think part of the reason we
bury people and we should bury amputated limbs as well is because
to prevent כהנים kohanim from coming in contact with טומאת מת, tumat
meit, to prevent כהנים kohanim from becoming impure from those things. So
then you would presume that אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, an
amputated limb, should be buried. But this גמרא gemara seems, the שבות
יעקב shevut yaakov quotes it at least as maybe one of the
few sources in ש"ס shas that suggests an amputated limb does not
need to be buried. He discusses it basically להלכה lehalacha we don't
think that this is acceptable or appropriate, but it's an interesting source
in the גמרא gemara to have. Is this what the גמרא gemara
is saying? The גמרא gemara is suggesting according to this גמרא gemara
sounds like you don't have to bury it. I understand. Okay, so
it's a מחלוקת. machloket. So it's a מחלוקת machloket within the גמרא
gemara and the way הלכה halacha has come down to us that
you do bury it. I hear that.
You do recently? Yeah?
The מילה milah there's a question of what to do with
the ערלה. arlah. That's a separate question also the amount of flesh.
It's not a body part that has a bone in it. It
has a very minimal amount of flesh. It's a different sort of,
you know, there are all these הלכות halachot in מסכת אהלות. masechet
ohalot. That's...
so the איברים eivarim that are מטמא metamei have to be... have
to have a bone and they have to have a certain amount
of flesh, כזית kezayit מטמא metamei or even things... so all those
kind of things, even a small limb because even if it's less
than a כזית kezayit but it has a bone, it has the
whole bone, so that becomes... so that's a whole... the bone is
separate to itself and there's a question of which ones are only
במגע ומשא bemaga umasa and which ones are באהל. beohel. The whole
מסכת אהלות masechet ohalot one of the most difficult מסכתות masechtot discusses
with that. Okay. So that's the discussion there. So this גמרא gemara
suggests at least that, you know, part of the בושת boshet involved
is that the person who is having this amputation, the limb will
be thrown to the dogs to eat. Okay. אלא אומדים כמה אדם
רוצה ליתן לקטוע ידו המוכתב למלכות. ela omdim kama adam rotzeh liten
likto'a yado hamukhtav lemalchut. So a person who is already sentenced to
have his hand cut off by the wicked government and now the
question is how much is he willing to pay to have it
done בין בסם לסייף. bein besam lesayif. That is, to do it
medically rather than as a punishment. That is, to be done with
medicines or something like that. kind of maybe we would say anesthetic
something like that compared to having it removed in a very painful
way. What? הנסי? Hanasi? Yeah, exactly. דאמרי הכא נמי לא שקיל מטרנא
נפשיה de'amri hacha nami lo shakil mitarna napshe אלא אמר רבא אדם
רוצה ליתן לקטוע לו ידו המוחתכת למלכות בין סייף לסם. ella amar
Rava adam rotze litein liktoa lo yado hamuchetachet lamalchut bein sayif lesam.
So היי לטול ליתן hai litol litein so what does it mean
לטול? litol? לטול litol means to take. But is it that he
is taking? In one place it is said ליתן. litein. So basically
מיבעיא ליה אלא אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לטול זה מזה.
mibaya lei ella amar Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua litol zeh mizeh.
So זה שנתן זה. zeh shenatan zeh. That is whenever there is
monetary exchange it might be called לטול litol to take the money
it might be called ליתן litein to give the money whatever use
the same word to describe opposite sides of the equation but they
they are the same process. Okay. So what about ריפוי? rippui? ריפוי
rippui הכהו hikahu so if a person hits someone חייב לרפותו hayav
lerapoto you have to heal him. Okay. So we say. So תנו
רבנן. tanu rabanan. What about the משנה mishna had said עלו בו
צמחים מחמת המכה alu bo tzmachim machmat hamakah if there were some
kind of scabs or growths that grew out after the injury because
of that injury ונסתרה המכה venistaracha hamakah mean complication?
Or some kind some kind of complications.
The wound healed up and it opened up again and healed up
and it opened up again right so ונסתרה המכה venistaracha hamakah חייב
לרפותו hayav lerapoto you still have an obligation to heal it וחייב
ליתן לו דמי שבתו vehayav litein lo dmei shivto and you have
to pay for time off of work we're going to see that
soon שלא מחמת המכה אינו חייב לרפותו ואינו חייב ליתן לו דמי
שבתו. shelo machmat hamakah eino hayav lerapoto veeino hayav litein lo dmei
shivto. You're not obligated if it it was not because of the
injury you're not obligated to heal it and you're not obligated to
pay for time off of work. רבי יהודה אומר אף מחמת המכה
חייב לרפותו ואינו חייב ליתן לו דמי שבתו. Rabbi Yehuda omer af
machmat hamakah hayav lerapoto veeino hayav litein lo dmei shivto. Rabbi Yehuda
says if there were growths that is some sort of extended injury
that keeps healing and reopening and healing and reopening so Rabbi Yehuda
would say in such a case you do have to pay the
ריפוי rippui you do have to pay medical expenses but you do
not have to pay time off of work for that kind of
protracted injury because the שבת shevet the time off of work should
only apply to the initial injury and not to the complications. וחכמים
אומרים שבתו ורפואתו כל שחייב בשבת חייב בריפוי.
vechachamim omrim shivto verifuato kol
shehayav beshevet hayav berippui. So חכמים chachamim say ריפוי rippui and שבת
shevet whatever one is obligated the other is obligated. They come together.
That's the תנא קמא tana kama right?
That that's the תנא קמא tana kama exactly.
So חכמים chachamim is it's just the response
it's the probably it's the גמרא gemara sort of explicating the שיטה
shita of חכמים chachamim in a more precise way. Okay. ושאינו חייב
בשבת אינו חייב בריפוי vesheino hayav beshevet eino hayav berippui and if
you're exempted from paying שבת shevet if you're exempt from paying for
time off of work then you're also exempt from paying for medical
expenses. במאי קמיפלגי אמר רבא דאשכחינהו לרבנן בבי
רב דיתבי וקאמרי הכא במכה ניתנה לאגד קמיפלגי.
bemai kamipalgi amar
Rava de'ashkeichinhu lerabanan bebeirav deyatvi veka'amri hacha bemakah nitna le'ageid kamipalgi.
They're talking about an injury that should be or how much should
it be appropriate to bandage a wound? Okay. Because we could understand
at least in their time the fewer bandages you have it's going
to hurt more now but it will heal faster. We know that
certain kind of bandages especially if they decrease amount of blood flow
to the wound could actually slow the healing process. So if you
put too many bandages or you wrap them too tightly it's going
to slow down the healing.
Is that the verb לאגד? le'ageid?
לאגד le'ageid to bind. It's like לולב צריך אגד lulav tzarich eged
right the לולב lulav has to be or אגד Egged the Israeli
bus company.
I just thought it was a noun I just thought so.
Oh yeah no ניתנה לאגד nitna le'ageid to be bound up. A
wound that is suitable or is appropriate to be bound up קמיפלגי.
kamipalgi. רבנן סברי מכה ניתנה לאגד. rabanan savrei makah nitna le'ageid. So
the rabbis that is חכמים chachamim think it is appropriate to bind
the wound and therefore even though it slows down the healing that's
part of the initial that's the proper way to deal with this
injury and therefore even if it takes a long time you should
pay שבת shevet as well. ורבי יהודה סבר מכה לא ניתנה לאגד.
veRabbi Yehuda savar makah lo nitna le'ageid. So and Rabbi Yehuda thinks
yeah the doctor might tell you to do that but fundamentally it's
not necessary for the healing therefore since you could let it heal
faster the fact that you're prolonging the healing is actually it's your
liability it's not the person who caused the injury's liability. So
so that becomes a question in you know in any kind of
this kind of ריפוי rippui evaluation is suppose a doctor gives you
two options. The doctor says you can have you know six months
of this kind of therapy but it's going to be and it's
be very slow and it's the safe route but it's a long
time. Or we could be done in a week and a half
but it's going to be very painful and it's going to be
higher risk.
Oh you have risk it might not heal properly.
So any of those kind of options the so if the doctor
gives you both options how do you say which is appropriate choice
which is inappropriate? How much שבת shevet do you have to pay
in that kind of a case? Those are all you know major
questions or even the ריפוי rippui question the doctor gives you two
options. There's the foolproof method that's going to cost this much and
there's a riskier option that might cost less or it might be
you know less painful or more experimental things like that but it's
going to have more risks involved. So all of those questions are
really going to raise the question of what's ניתנה לאגד nitna le'ageid
what what is actually the proper way to deal with this wound
or injury and how do you how do you evaluate that? Okay.
So ריפוי... rippui... ריפוי דתנא בקרא מחייב שבת דלא תנא בקרא לא
מחייב. Ripuy detana bekra mechayev sheves delo tana bekra lo mechayev. So
in that case that is Rabbi Yehuda's שיטה shitta is that ריפוי
ripuy because the Torah had obligated it that you're still obligated to
pay ריפוי ripuy because the Torah made it explicit that you still
have to pay for the ריפוי ripuy but not the שבת. sheves.
What do you mean, Rashi says ורפא ירפא verapo yerape basically שבת.
sheves. You have to pay שבת sheves but only שבת sheves during
the appropriate time of
the ריפוי, ripuy, not for the entire time it actually takes to
heal. And how do you know to
make
that
distinction? And that's Rabbi Yehuda's because the Torah's not clear either way.
I agree. Rashi says it's על פי דעתו. al pi da'ato.
He's choosing this. Right, like that's the point, the discretionary aspect of
this. He's likely to extend this treatment option. Right.
So then you still have to pay for however much the healing
process costs because that's still part of the injury, but the שבת,
sheves, the time off work, you wouldn't have to pay. Okay.
Okay. ואמינא להו אנא, veamina lehu ana, אם מכה לא ניתנה לאגד,
im maka lo nitna leaged, so then the rabbis can respond to
Rabbi Yehuda. If the injury is not meant to be bound up,
okay, so ריפוי נמי לא מיחייב, ripuy nami lo mechayev, why should
he have to pay for his choice to have it medically treated
in this way if you think that that's not appropriate? אלא לכולי
עלמא מכה ניתנה לאגד, ella lechulei alma maka nitna leaged, rather everyone
agrees that the right way to deal with this wound is that
you should wrap it up with this bandage, ולא ניתנה לאגד יתירה,
velo nitna leaged yetira, but that you shouldn't
over-bind it because that's going to slow down the healing. רבי יהודה
סבר כיון דלא ניתנה לאגד יתירה ריפוי דתנא בקרא מחייב שבת דלא
תנא בקרא לא מחייב. Rabbi Yehuda savar keivan delo nitna leaged yetira
ripuy detana bekra mechayev sheves delo tana bekra lo mechayev. So Rabbi
Yehuda thinks since you should not do it too much, therefore that
gets you off the hook for שבת, sheves, but since it's part
of the ריפוי ripuy clause in general, you still have to pay
for the ריפוי ripuy in that case.
ורבנן
סברי, verabbanan savrei, and the rabbis think, כיון דתנא בקרא בריפוי שבת
נמי מחייב,
keivan detana bekra
beripuy sheves nami mechayev, דאיקש לריפוי, de'ikesh leripuy, and the rabbis think
that שבת sheves and ריפוי ripuy you always pay together because they're
connected. The פסוק pasuk says like Michael quoted, רק שבתו יתן, rak
shivto yiten, you have to pay for שבת, sheves, ורפא ירפא, verapo
yerape, you have to heal the person as well. So each of
those clauses according to the rabbis, according to חכמים, chachamim, because they're
connected, you pay one when you pay the other. So whatever medical
route the person takes that's based on appropriate medical advice obviously,
then you would have to pay שבת sheves throughout that period as
well.
I'm not understanding. So what does the אגד יתירה aged yetira have
to do with שבת? sheves?
Because the אגד יתירה aged yetira will slow down the healing and
therefore you're going to have a longer period of time when you're
off of work. And therefore that'll incur a greater cost for שבת.
sheves.
But you're not talking about an אגד יתירה aged yetira case.
No, he is. That's exactly what we're talking about. That's the אוקימתא.
ukimta. The גמרא gemara has said that that's the אוקימתא ukimta that
we have to make for this מחלוקת machlokes between חכמים chachamim and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is that they're talking about אגד יתירה, aged
yetira, that is something which is medically sometimes suggested. חכמים chachamim think
that that's an appropriate course of action, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks
it's actually a bad course of action because it slows down the
healing too much. Or at least from the perspective of נזיקין, nezikin,
if you go down that route, we can't make this other person
liable because you had another option. You could have chosen the faster
route which would have again המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'aya. We're trying to get someone to pay for someone else's time
off of work. We're trying to get someone to pay for someone
else's medical expenses. So in order to actually make him pay, you
have to have a high threshold of proof. Okay. רבי יהודה סבר
שבת לא מחייב מטעם דרחמנא רק.
Rabbi Yehuda savar sheves lo mechayev
mita'am derachmana rak. So why does Rabbi Yehuda reject the-
so this is medical malpractice, why should I pay?
It's not malpractice that they're both options.
Yeah, but אגד יתירה aged yetira is a bad thing.
According to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda he thinks it's a bad thing
from the perspective of נזיקין, nezikin, that is it slows down the
healing. So the fact that you're trying to now say 'I did
this medical practice', well but you could have done it faster and
therefore I don't have to pay your שבת sheves because you could
have done it faster. Okay.
So אגד יתירה aged yetira doesn't mean malpractice, it just means?
I don't think it means malpractice, it means you have two options.
One is fast and one is slow.
Look, my dental plan will pay for a plastic crown or it'll
pay for a porcelain crown. I have two options. I could get
plastic, it's paid for, but porcelain is- it'll last my whole life,
but they're not going to pay for the porcelain. Right. But let's
say you know you pick this doctor and then there is malpractice
under.
Malpractice is a separate question, right? We're going to get to malpractice
today as well, but we have to keep going. Okay.
But would he have to pay at least to the amount that
it would have?
Correct. Amount of time from the regular שבת. sheves. Correct. Okay. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda why does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reject the היקש
hekesh between ריפוי ripuy and שבת? sheves? Because the פסוק pasuk says
דאמר רחמנא רק, deamar rachmana rak, because it says רק שבתו יתן.
rak shivto yiten. רק. rak. רק rak means you would only pay
שבת sheves under the limited circumstances even if you would be paying
ריפוי. ripuy. ורבנן, verabbanan, רק rak לשלא מחמת המכה הוא דאתא. lishlo
machamat hamaka hu deata. The rabbis interpret רק rak differently, that is
you pay שבת sheves even to exclude things which are not because
of the injury. ורבנן בתראי verabbanan batrai דאמרי כל שחייב בשבת חייב
בריפוי, deamri kol shechayev beshabbos chayav beripuy,
and the rabbis therefore learn that the פסוק pasuk says כל. kol.
So כל kol comes to teach that שבת sheves and ריפוי ripuy
are equated. The
fact that the תורה Torah repeated the word ריפוי, rippui, רפא ירפא
rappo yerappe was repeated, okay, so למה לי מיבעי לכדתניא. lama li
mibaei lechiditanya. So why does the פסוק pasuk say רפא ירפא, rappo
yerappe, a double language? Because we have to learn the דרשה drasha
of the תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. tana devei Rabbi Yishmael. The תנא
tana from the school of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, דתניא דבי רבי
ישמעאל אומר ורפא ירפא, detanya devei Rabbi Yishmael omer verappo yerappe, you
should surely heal it, heal heal. מכאן שניתן רשות לרופא לרפאות. mikan
she'nitan reshut lerofei lerapeit.
There is permission granted for doctors to heal. Now the question is
why does a doctor need permission? What does it mean permission?
So that's part of the question. If you look in תוספות Tosafot
here, שניתן רשות לרופא לרפאות, she'nitan reshut lerofei lerapeit, a doctor has
permission to heal. ואם תאמר המרפא לחולים, ve'im tomar hammerapei lacholim, okay,
יש לומר דהוה אמינא הני מילי מכה בידי אדם.
yesh lomar de'hava amina
hanei milei maka bidei adam. Maybe a doctor is only allowed to
heal injuries that a person caused. That is what the תורה Torah
is talking about. But your הוה אמינא hava amina would have been
that an injury or an illness that comes from God, that is
totally naturally caused, okay, if you're going to go and try to
heal that, נראה כסותר גזירת המלך. nir'eh kesoter gzeirat hamelech. You're going
against God's will. Right? Isn't this what some religions believe? Right? A
person contracts a certain illness and then they say, okay, I'm not
going to take any medical medical treatment. Whatever God wants to do
for me, God should do. גזירת המלך. gzeirat hamelech. I believe that
that's God punishing me or something like that. So we say קא
משמע לן דשרי. kamashma lan deshari. No, this comes to teach that
even for illnesses, that is even things that are caused by disease,
things caused, sent by God, nonetheless human beings have the right and
perhaps an obligation to heal those as well. We have to see
the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't quote this דרשה. drasha. Now the רמב"ם Rambam
was a doctor. The רמב"ם Rambam wasn't—doesn't quote this דרשה drasha that
says there's רשות, reshut, there's permission. So why? Because the רמב"ם Rambam
thinks it's not permission, it's an obligation. The רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש
המשנה peirush hamishnah to מסכת נדרים masechet nedarim learns the obligation to
be to provide medical healing is from the sense of והשבתו לו
ve'hashevato lo by השבת אבידה, hashavat aveidah, returning a lost object, and
he makes a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. That's right. If you have
to return someone's property, קל וחומר kal vachomer that if they're sick
you have to return their health to them, return their life to
them. So the רמב"ם Rambam learns actually a more even more extreme
version of the sense of medical responsibility. A few other points. The
point about גזירת המלך, gzeirat hamelech, רמב"ן, Ramban, רמב"ן Ramban also was
a doctor. So רמב"ן Ramban in פרשת בחקתי parshat bechukotai talks about
a much debated passage that talks about how much רמב"ן Ramban might
have thought that it's actually inappropriate to go to doctors, to demonstrate
a lack of faith. You don't believe that God can heal you,
right? God is רופא חולים, rophei cholim, not human beings. So much
debated, but the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer in discussing that, the ציץ
אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer was a master of medical הלכה halacha and has
many many volumes about medical questions in his תשובות. teshuvot. So he
discusses this רמב"ן Ramban and he says we know from רמב"ן Ramban
himself, his other writings, that obviously you're supposed to go to doctors.
He himself was a doctor. The רמב"ן Ramban in פרשת בחקתי parshat
bechukotai was talking about a time when there are obvious miracles in
everyday life. So if there are obvious miracles then you can believe
then for sure if God is doing miracles, God will be able
to heal you without going to a doctor. But בזמן הזה, bazman
hazeh, the life we live, the society we live, obviously the appropriate
choice is to go to the doctor.
Okay.
So תנו רבנן, tnu rabbanan, מניין שאם עלו בו צמחים מחמת המכה
ונסתרה המכה שחייב לרפאותו וחייב ליתן לו שבתו. minayin she'im alu bo
tzmachim machmat hamaka venistera hamaka shechayav lerapoto vechayav litein lo shivto. So
how do we know that in a case where there was some
kind of growth that came out of this wound and then it
opened up again and it healed again and opened up again and
it healed again, so if it's all מחמת המכה, machmat hamaka, if
it's all because of this injury, you still have to pay ריפוי
rippui and you still have to pay שבת. shevet. Okay. תלמוד לומר
רק Talmud lomar rak. שבתו יתן ורפא ירפא. v'rapo yirape יכול אפילו
שלא מחמת המכה. yakhol afilu shelo machmat hamaka. So could you think
that it even would apply if it's not something that was caused
by the injury?
Because the פסוק pasuk seems to be very inclusive. תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar רק. rak. Because the תורה Torah says רק. rak. So רק
rak comes to exclude. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר Rabbi Yossi bar
Yehuda omer אף מחמת המכה פטור. af machmat hamaka patur. He says
even if it's because of the injury, you're פטור patur from paying
for an extended wound that keeps opening and closing, opening and closing.
שנאמר shene'emar רק. rak. Because of the word רק rak comes even
to exclude something like that. איכא דאמרי ikka de'amri אף מחמת המכה
פטור לגמרי. af machmat hamaka patur legamrei. So then there are some
people who would say even פטור לגמרי, patur legamrei, you're totally exempt
for an injury like that.
כרבנן בתראי דאיכא דאמרי אף מחמת המכה פטור משבת וחייב בריפוי כמאן
כאבוה.
kerabbanan batrai de'ikka de'amri af machmat
hamaka patur mishabbet vechayav berippui kman ke'avuh. So the whole back and
forth here is that there are a lot of איכא דאמרי ikka
de'amris and it gets tricky for the ראשונים rishonim to figure out
how to פסקן pasken in those kind of cases, what the conclusion
of the סוגיא sugya is, but at least the way it seems
here is that certainly איכא דאמרי, ikka de'amri, the final voice, is
that we would say אף מחמת המכה פטור לגמרי, af machmat hamaka
patur legamrei, that you might say actually that you should if it's
not anything related to the injury, even if it is related to
the injury, if it's something extended, protracted, you probably are exempt, and
then also that in such a case you might be exempt from
paying שבת shevet but you would
still. So that's כדאבוה דשמואל Kedavuh deshmuel we saw right going
back and רבנן בתראי? Rabanan batra'ei? רבנן בתראי Rabanan batra'ei was the
second rabbis' opinion
in this whole סוף השמועה. sof hashmua. That is the opinion of
רבנן Rabanan who said that about the about the אגידתי תיירי agidtei
tayeiri that you're protracting the illness or protracting the healing, so in
that case you would be exempt.
Okay.
אמר מר יכול אפילו שלא מחמת המכה. Amar mar yachol afilu shelo
machmat hamaka. So is it possible that you would have to pay
even in a case where the where the wound was not actually
caused by the injury? תלמוד לומר רק שלא מחמת המכה. Talmud lomar
rak shelo machmat hamaka. Okay. So שלא מחמת המכה באי קרא? shelo
machmat hamaka ba'i kra? So does the Torah have to even tell
me that? That's so obvious. What, if I get an injury that
has nothing to do with the fact that the person hit me,
so why should he have to pay for it, right? Okay. So
אמרי מאי שלא מחמת המכה? Amrei mai shelo machmat hamaka? What does
it mean that it's not because of the injury? כדתניא הרי שעבר
על דברי רופא. Kedatanya harei she'avar al divrei rofe. I don't know,
it's because you didn't listen to the doctor. That's the question. ואכל
דבש ve'achal devash and you ate honey because obviously they knew that
sugar is bad for you, at least at certain times, או
כל מיני מתיקה מפני שדבש וכל מיני מתיקה קשים למכה o kol
minei metika mipnei shedvash vekol minei metika kashim lamaka because sugar is
if you eat sugar while you're sick it's going to make it
slower to heal. והעלה מכתו גרגרתני. vehe'ela makato gargetani. What word is
that? גרגרתני. Gargetani.
Like
it got some kind of a scab or growth. יכול יהיה חייב
לרפותו. Yachol yihiye chayav lerafoto. Is it true that in that case
then if the person punched me and then it was healing fine
and then I went and ate candy and then it got this
horrible scab and now I have to go to the doctor, is
that his fault? No, it's my fault. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar רק.
So מאי גרגרתני? mai gargetani? So אמר אביי נטא כריכתא. amar Abaye
nata krichta. It's some kind of like a bound up dead skin
lesion, right?
The רש"י Rashi says בשר מת basar
met so it gets into the gangrenous question or the necrosis of
the skin. Okay. So obviously these are kind of things that hopefully
people don't ever have to deal with themselves. So מאי אסותא? mai
asuta? אהלא כהירי וכלבא. Ahala kehiri vechalba. ואי אמר ליה אסיך אנא.
ve'i amar lei asich ana. אמר ליה... amar lei...
okay, let me see... one
second...
one second...
אהלא Ahala as aloe.
Yeah. אהלא Ahala is aloe and כהירי kehiri is wax. Right, let
me take a look in the next one because there are a
lot of words here that I thought I had prepared well enough
and no, not not as well as I thought. One second.
Okay.
All right. One second.
All right.
When he says
אסיך אנא asich ana he says back to him דמיתנא לי כאריה
ארבא.
damitna li ke'arya arba. Right, so how you cure this נטא כריכתא,
nata krichta, so either you put אהלא ahala which is aloe, right,
כהירי kehiri is wax, and כלבא chalba is a certain kind of
a resin or a sap, the pitch from the trees. Okay. Okay.
ואי אמר ליה אסיך אנא.
ve'i amar lei
asich ana. I'll heal you myself. I'll be the doctor, right? The
guy who punched him says okay I'm going to deal with it.
Okay. So אמר ליה דמית לי כאריה ארבא. amar lei damit li
ke'arya arba. So he'll say back to him like what you're the
lion? You're the guy who beat me up. Why am I going
to trust you to be my doctor? Right? So that's the question.
Okay. So in other words the person doesn't think to say okay
it'll be cheaper if I do it myself so I'll offer to
do it myself, so the person can refuse. The person gets to
choose their doctor basically, that's part of this question.
Okay. ואי אמר ליה מייתינא אסיא דמגן במגן. ve'i amar lei maitina
asya demagan bemagan. So what if a person is going to come...
what if there's a doctor who's willing to treat you pro bono?
So I'll go negotiate you a doctor who's going to do it
pro bono.
אלוהים יעזור. Elohim ya'azor.
I guess he's allowed to go out of the system and choose
some... okay nevermind go ahead. Okay so מייתינא אסיא דמגן במגן. maitina
asya demagan bemagan. So what can he say back to him? אמר
ליה אסיא דמגן במגן מגן שוה. amar lei asya demagan bemagan magan
shaveh. So a person who a doctor who's working for free doesn't
do as good a job, he's worthless as a doctor. Why? Because
there's a presumption that the amount of monetary
motivation to do a good job, that is a sort of a
basic notion of capitalism is that if people are getting paid they're
going to do a better job than if they're not getting paid.
People who go do volunteer work sometimes might feel that.
Can you just translate... what's the word מגן
במגן? magan bemagan?
מגן Magan to be like to the cost.
דמגן במגן Demagan bemagan to pay... מגן Magan is a...
I think it's like... like it's an Aramaic word like... like שכר
sachar some kind of a שכר. sachar. All right. Like free for
free.
Free for free, or if he's
free he's מגן שוה. magan shaveh. So the other question is going
back to the question of ניתן רשות לרופא לרפאות, Nitan Reshut L'Rofeh
L'Rapot, so the דעת זקנים מן התורה, Da'at Zekenim Min HaTorah, from
the בעלי התוספות, Ba'alei HaTosafot, one of the commentaries on the תורה
Torah says, obviously a doctor is allowed to be a doctor. That's
not the question. There's no other profession the תורה Torah feels like
is necessary to say, oh this profession they have a right to
do their job. The question is how much are you allowed to
charge for being a doctor? Because maybe you'll say it's a מצוה
mitzvah to be a doctor, you're healing someone, you're helping someone, so
you should have to do it for free because it's a מצוה.
mitzvah. Comes the תורה Torah ורפא ירפא verapo yerape. to say that
you actually have to pay for medical expenses, exactly this point, which
is that a doctor who's being paid is going to perform better
than a doctor who has to work pro bono. Okay. ואי
אמר מאיתנא לך אסיא רחיקא, v'ee amar maitna lach asya rechika, I'll
bring you a doctor from a faraway country, maybe he's a better
doctor but it's going to cost more, or maybe he'll cost less.
Okay, I guess it'll cost less. The doctors here are very expensive,
I'll go bring you a doctor from Mexico who will charge you
half as much. The guy
says אסיא רחיקא עינא עוירא, asya rechika eina avira, a faraway eye
is a blind eye, or a doctor from far away either has
a blind eye that he doesn't know what's going on here, or
he could make your eye blind. That is, a doctor from far
away doesn't understand the way people around here live or what their
diet is or things like that. Or because he's leaving, he'll leave
eventually, he's not going to care about the long-term results, there's no
follow-up. So all of those kind of questions, so these are major
questions, you could go through these סוגיא sugya very בעיון b'iyun and
look at all the ראשונים Rishonim and really draw it out to
figure out what modern doctors, how are they supposed to act and
what kind of things we can learn about in our lives as
well. Okay. ואי אמר ליה הב לי לדידי ואנא מסינא נפשאי, v'ee
amar lei hav li l'didi v'ana masina nafshai, so what if he
says, just give me the money and I'll go find a doctor
for myself. Okay, so אמר ליה פשעת בנפשך ושקלת מינאי טפי, amar
lei pashat b'nafshecha v'shaklat minai tafi, so you'll be negligent and you'll
try to charge me more. That is what? If I let you
be totally responsible for your own recovery, you're going to try to
scam me. Now, obviously it's kind of a strange suggestion because what?
Because a person is going to put their own life at risk,
put their own health at risk just to try to earn back
the amount of money that it was going to cost to heal,
they're not going to make any money off of that. But that's
at least this kind of scam that they're worried about, so they
don't allow that. ואי אמר ליה קוץ לי מינך, v'ee amar lei
kutz li minach, what if he says, set a fixed price now
and just fix that? That is, there's no way that it's going
to be variable, it's not going to be based on actually how
much it costs and that way the person won't worry about trying
to slow down their healing to overcharge. אמר ליה כל שכן דפשעת
בנפשך, amar lei kol sheken d'pashat b'nafshecha, no, all the more so
then in that case you're going to try to be negligent, so
people were going to make fun of me, they're going to see
that you didn't get better because I didn't give you enough money
to heal, and then they're going to say דקרו לי שור המזיק.
d'karu li shor hamazik. They're going to call me שור המזיק. shor
hamazik. Now, of course the literary point here to connect between אדם
המזיק adam hamazik and שור המזיק, shor hamazik, right? A שור המזיק
shor hamazik doesn't pay ריפוי. ripuy. So the point is if a
person was injured by an ox and then goes and collects נזק,
nezek, then the person is never getting paid for their medical expenses.
So obviously in this case of a person being underpaid for medical
expenses, trying to close the deal early, then the person is going
to have lasting complications, it's going to look like שור המזיק shor
hamazik because with שור המזיק shor hamazik also you don't get paid
for your medical needs and so then that recovery, there'll be medical
complications that come out of that. So a person would be worried
about being compared to שור המזיק. shor hamazik. He says I'm okay
if people know that I'm the guy who stabbed you as long
as you heal okay, so people don't think I'm a שור shor
that gored you. Well, it's more brutal, it's more inhuman.
Is it even today from antiquity, doctors are pledged to do no
harm and אדם מועד לעולם? adam muad l'olam? Exactly.
That's another part of the רשות לרופא reshut l'rofe is אדם מועד
לעולם. adam muad l'olam. What if a doctor causes, like you said,
negligence, if they cause
damage by what they just do?
Right, and he'd be, so then the question is, does a doctor,
what if a doctor has a malpractice question? The doctor thought this
would be beneficial and it turns out it's not, or a doctor
made a mistake. So that's why a doctor needs a certain amount
of רשות. reshut. You have to put yourself in the risk of
trying to do something good and then there might be complications. Okay.
The גמרא Gemara continues, okay?
The גמרא Gemara continues, תניא, tanya, there's a ברייתא: braita: וכולן משתלמין
במקום נזק. v'chulan mishtalmin bimkom nezek. So all of them, that is
all the other four, get paid in the place of במקום, bimkom,
meaning when you pay נזק nezek you also pay those other ones
as well. And that really means that נזק nezek doesn't exempt you
from paying the other four. That is, the נזק nezek is limited
to the damage itself and the other four cover other parts of
the experience. Okay, so תניא דכולהו משתלמי במקום נזק. tanya d'chulhu mishtalmei
bimkom nezek. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? So where do we
learn this from? אמר רב זביד משמיה דרבא אמר קרא פצע תחת
פצע. amar Rav Zevid mishmeih d'Rava amar kra petza tachat petza. You
have to
pay, whatever פצע petza is, a wound for a wound. Okay, ליתן
צער במקום נזק, leitein tza'ar bimkom nezek, so that teaches you that
you pay צער tza'ar for pain and suffering when you also are
paying for the נזק, nezek, that is the damage, which we already
discussed at length the מחלוקת machloket about that between בן עזאי Ben
Azzai and רבי. Rebbi. Okay. So האי מיבעי ליה לירבות hai mibaei
lei leirabot לירבות שוגג כמזיד ואונס כרצון. leirabot shogeg k'mezid ve'oneis k'ratzon.
But don't we need פצע תחת פצע pessa tachat pessa to include
אדם המזיק adam hamazik has to pay, a person who causes injury
has to pay either in cases of שוגג כמזיד, shogeg k'mezid, you
have to pay even if it was unintentional as if it was
intentional, אונס כרצון, oneis k'ratzon, or if it was totally accidental as
if it was you had awareness of
it? אם כן im kein נכתוב קרא nichtov kra פצע בפצע. pessa
b'pessa. It could have said wound by wound, פצע בפצע pessa b'pessa
or פצע בפצע. pessa b'pessa. מאי פצע תחת פצע? mai pessa tachat
pessa? A wound for a wound? שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina tarti.
We can learn both from that because there's an additional- a sense
of redundancy in the פסוק. passuk. רב פפא משמיה דרבא אמר, Rav
Pappa mishmei deRava amar, רב פפא Rav Pappa quoted from רבא, Rava,
אמר, amar, אמר קרא amar kra ורפא ירפא. So the פסוק passuk
says you have to heal for it, ליתן רפואה במקום נזק. litein
refuah b'makom nezek. So that's where it's learned you have to pay
רפואה refuah even when you're also paying for the נזק. nezek. והאי
מיבעי ליה לכדתניא ve'hai mibaei lei lechadetanya דבי רבי ישמעאל, debei Rebbe
Yishmael, that's like the תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tanna debei Rebbe Yishmael
who already said שניתן רשות לרופא לרפאות. shenitan reshut l'rofe l'rapot. אם
כן im kein נכתוב רחמנא nichtov Rachmana ורפא ורפא, v'rapo v'rapo, and
he should heal, ירפא ירפא. yerape yerape. שמע מינה shma mina
ליתן רפואה במקום נזק. litein refuah b'makom nezek.
So the redundancy is learned to apply to both, that is there's
a permission for doctors to heal and you have to pay ריפוי
במקום נזק. ripui b'makom nezek. והדר מיבעי ליה לכדאמרן v'hadar mibaei lei
lechadamran ומייתי בה קרא בריפוי. u'meiti bah kra b'ripui. But
then so how can you say that that applies to- the פסוק
passuk applies to that you're obligated to pay ריפוי? ripui? אם כן
im kein לימא קרא leima kra או רפו רפו o rapo rapo
או
ירפה ירפה, o yerape yerape, פירודי שה רפו רפו pirudei she rapo
rapo או ירפה ירפה. o yerape yerape. So the fact that it
switches רפו ירפה. rapo yerape. מאי רפו ירפה? mai rapo yerape? שמע
מינה shma mina ליתן רפואה במקום נזק. litein refuah b'makom nezek. You
have to pay ריפוי ripui even when you're paying for נזק nezek
as well. אבל משכחת להו שלא במקום נזק? aval mishkachat lehu shelo
b'makom nezek? Ah, but that must imply that there is such a
case where you would pay ריפוי ripui even if there's no
נזק. nezek. שלא במקום נזק היכי משכחת להו? shelo b'makom nezek heichi
mishkachat lehu? What cases is that? צער. tzar. So it must be
a case of צער. tzar. That is in a case of צער
tzar where you would pay צער tzar you could also pay ריפוי
ripui even if there's no נזק, nezek, even if there's no lasting
damage. Why? Because it could take some cost to actually heal that
temporary
injury. לכדתניא lechadetanya צער tzar כוואו בשפוד ובמסמר. k'va'o b'shipud u've'masmer. With
this price we already saw that if a person burns someone else
with
a- a stake or a nail, אפילו על ציפורנו afilu al tziporno
even on his fingernail, מקום שאינו עושה חבורה makom she'eino oseh chavura
a place that doesn't create a bruise, ריפוי דהווא קא כאיב ליה.
ripui d'hava ka ka'iv lei.
So the fact that it hurts him he also has to have
some kind of a heal, he has to have some kind of
medical expense.
מאי דקא
כאיב ליה? mai d'ka ka'iv lei? מידי דמסלק אייתי ליה סמא חריפא.
midi d'misalak aiti lei
sama charifa. So you have to give some kind of a very
sharp
medicine, the ointment is going to burn very much or it's very
sharp, ואחורה לבישרא v'achvara l'bisra and it bleached your skin, וצריך למוטי
ביה סמא לאנקוטי
גוון דבישרא. v'tzarich l'motei bei sama l'ankutei gavan d'bisra. And then you
have to give another medicine that's going to bring back color into
your flesh. Okay. So in that case, and שבת shevet דהדקיה באדורנא
d'hadkeia b'adorna
that
you- that when the person- so what is שבת? shevet? So דהדקיה
באדורנא d'hadkeia b'adorna or a person locked someone else in the room
or he closed him up in a box ובטליה u'vatlei and he
got him off work. That is if someone locks you up- so
they didn't cause you any physical damage but they still took you
off of work. So that could be שבת shevet just by itself
and no נזק nezek and no ריפוי ripui and no צער tzar
but it was still time off of work. So בשת boshet and
when could there be a case of בשת boshet without any of
the others? בשת דרק ליה באפיה boshet d'rak lei b'apei if a
person spit at someone else in the face. That is it's embarrassing
but it doesn't cause any kind of physical damage, it doesn't cause
you to take time off of work, maybe a minute here a
minute there but that's not enough to be really evaluated. Okay. Next
few more minutes, let's see how far we can get. Okay. So
שבת רואין אותו כאילו הוא שומר קישואין. shevet ro'in oto k'ilu hu
shomer kishu'in. When we are evaluating שבת shevet we have a certain
halachic minimum wage it seems. The halachic minimum wage seems to be
the amount of money that a person gets paid to serve as
the watchman over a field of squash, like zucchinis or something. So
we have to see what. So תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. The Rabbis
taught, שבת shevet רואין אותו כאילו הוא שומר קישואין. ro'in oto k'ilu
hu shomer kishu'in. We assess him as if he is a squash
watchman. ואם תאמר לקתה מידת הדין. v'im tomar lakta midat hadin. But
if you say it's not the measure of justice. So what do
you mean? Meaning is that really fair? Like it's not really fair.
Why? דכי מיפח האי גברא לאו אגר דשומר קישואין הוא. d'chi mifach
hai gavra lav agar d'shomer kishu'in hu. Because a person is going
to get up, he's going to be healed and he's not going
to be paid to be a squash watchman, zucchini watchman. Why? Rather
אלא דלי דובלא ושקיל אגרא. ela dali duvla v'shakil agra.
He's going to go work as a laborer to carry water, to
draw water for people and he'll get paid higher
wages. אינמי אדרא ושקיל אגרא. einami adra v'shakil agra. Or he'll work
as a messenger, bike messenger maybe something like that, delivering packages and
doing people's butlering tasks.
These are all alternative standards for שבת. sheves.
Right, but what it's saying is that is it really fair to
have such a low minimum wage if this person once he heals
is certainly not going to be working as the watchman? He's going
to work for a job that has a higher paying rate.
Right. Even if he can't go back to what he had been
doing before, there are other standards that you could apply. That's the
way I'm... Is that... You think that that's the correct reading? Right.
Why do the lowest?
Right. Why do the lowest? And what do they say? So the
גמרא gemara responds מדת הדין לא לקתה. middat hadin lo lakta. No,
it's not any damage done to the מדת הדין, middat hadin, to
the sense of justice, to the sense of fairness, why?
שכבר נתן לו
דמי ידו ודמי רגלו.
shekvar natan
lo dmei yado udmei raglo.
The fact that you already paid him for the injury. That is,
the person who had his hand cut off, you paid him the
cost difference between a slave who has a hand and a slave
who doesn't have a hand. So what does that mean? That includes
the sense of how much money he's going to be able to
earn even over a long period of time, many years, because that's
the sense of how much he would sell for as a slave.
And therefore,
in that case, you've already paid for that damage done to his
earning power. Now the only thing you're paying is a very minimum
sense of this person has no work at all because he's recovering
at home compared to the fact that he could be working a
little bit. So that sense of a little bit of earnings, a
very minimal sense of job, again, with all ממונות mamonos we have
to always go back to the core principle מוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה.
motzi mechavero alav hareaya. We're trying to take someone else's money to
pay for your expense, to pay for your time off of work.
So we have to use a fair threshold in that sense as
well, which is we're trying to... we have to have burden of
proof and we have to have a threshold of what's considered appropriate
to actually take someone else's money. So the reason why it's such
a low threshold is because you already paid for something which is
actually have a protracted effect on his earning power, that is the
injury done to his hand or to his foot. And now the
only question is well what is the bare minimum that he could
be earning at this point compared to nothing? Better than nothing.
What's the criterion that workman's compensation is calculated?
I have no idea for that either. Right.
Nor do I, but it's sort of a... but it's a similar...
Right. The same kind of question. Yeah. Okay. אמר
רבא. amar rava. So what does רבא rava say?
Okay. אמר רבא, amar rava, קטע ידו נותן לו דמי ידו ושבת
רואין אותו כאילו הוא שומר קישואין. kata yado noten lo dmei yado
vesheves roin oto keilu hu shomer kishuin. So if you cut off
someone's hand, you pay him for the hand, that is the injury,
and שבת, sheves, you calculate time off of work as if he's
a שומר קישואין, shomer kishuin, the watchman for the zucchinis. שיבר את
רגלו, shiber et raglo, if you broke someone's foot, נותן לו דמי
רגלו ושבת רואין אותו כאילו הוא שומר הפתח. noten lo dmei raglo
vesheves roin oto keilu hu shomer hapetach.
You assess him if he is a guardian at the gate, at
the door. So why a different kind of שומר? shomer? And סימא
את עינו, sima et eino, if you blinded someone's eye, נותן לו
דמי עינו ושבת רואין אותו כאילו הוא מטחינו
בריחיים. noten lo dmei eino vesheves roin oto keilu hu matchino bereichayim.
He's working as a grinder at the millstone. Why? Because that's a
job that doesn't require your eye at all. What's the difference? If
you have no hand, you could still be a שומר קישואין. shomer
kishuin. You can walk around the field and inspect and keep the
birds away, but you can't do any manual labor because you have
only one hand, or you could do very limited amount of manual
labor. Person who's broken his foot has to sit in one place,
so he has to be שומר הפתח. shomer hapetach. He has to
work at the toll booth, he has to work at the front
gate of the city because he has to have a sitting down
kind of a job. That person who was blinded, that person has
to have a job, is assessed at whatever kind of a job
is a job that you would be able to do while blind.
The question is whether some of these are actually even paid less
than the שומר קישואין, shomer kishuin,
presumably because they have lower... lower demand. Okay. מטחינו בריחיים, matchino bereichayim,
חירשו, chersho, and what if a person made someone else deaf? נותן
לו דמי כולו. noten lo dmei kulo. You pay for his entire
worth as a person, that is his slave value as a whole
person. Why? Because presumably, and again this is based on the rabbinic
understanding, the חירש, chersh, a person who's deaf, is understood to have
been a person who had no mental competence at all and was
unable to function normally in society in any way, unable to communicate,
unable to work. So in that sense, a person has a much
higher liability in terms of נזק nezek because they've incapacitated this person
entirely, and at the same time, there's no שבת sheves because the
person has no potential working value at all. Obviously, the evaluation of
the חירש chersh in modern times has changed significantly since the invention
and discovery of really, or really re-analysis of what it means to
be deaf and new ways that people who are deaf are able
to communicate, obviously sign language and all other sorts of things, and
a textual culture as opposed to a spoken culture and all sorts
of things, obviously people who are deaf have much higher capability now
than they did in the time of the גמרא. gemara.
In that category, in contemporary meaning, the category would be brain
injury.
Totally debilitated to the point where they cannot work, cannot communicate and
really is totally unable to function in society at all. And obviously
that kind of a thing is very different than deaf people in
our society now. We'll stop there, time is up, and we'll continue
tomorrow.